Okay, today's דף daf is קידושין Kiddushin כ"ב, Kaf Bet, קידושין Kiddushin
22. קידושין Kiddushin 22, we pick up on כ"א עמוד ב', Kaf
Aleph Amud Bet, we're a little behind. We pick up from the
two dots about eight lines from the top, and we're on to
the next section of the משנה. Mishnah. משנה Mishnah is talking about
how you acquire an עבד עברי Eved Ivri
and here we move on to the נרצע, Nirtza, the עבד עברי
Eved Ivri who is going to stay forever or until the יובל.
Yovel. והנרצע נקנה ברציעה. Ve'hanirtza nikneh birtziah. So the one who has
his ear pierced is acquired through the piercing of the ear. That's
and then he works until the יובל. Yovel. דכתיב, D'chsiv, the גמרא
Gemara says: ורצע אדוניו את אזנו במרצע. Veratza adonav et ozno bamorzea.
Fine, that's a פסוק. posuk. Okay. וקונה את עצמו ביובל ובמיתת האדון.
Vekoneh et atzmo b'yovel u'vemisas ha'adon. And acquires himself through the יובל
Yovel and the death of the master. דכתיב D'chsiv ועבדו va'avado ולא
את הבן ולא את הבת. velo es haben velo es habas. So
this יובל Yovel is in the פסוק. posuk. How do we know
that the נרצע Nirtza does not continue working gets free when the
master dies? Because it says ועבדו, va'avado, serve him, ולא את הבן
ולא את הבת. velo es haben velo es habas. Okay, and not
the son and not the daughter. לעולם, Le'olam, so when he dies
the master dies he goes free. This is different than for six
years. Six years is more like a שכירות, schirus, so the שכירות
schirus like you know hired worker, so that even does continue working
for the son although for the son I should say although not
for when it's not a direct inheritance by the son, if it
goes to any other relative, not.
But by the נרצע Nirtza goes free when the master dies. There's
a sense of total ownership so there's also a sense of the
death frees him. It's less a sense of שכירות. schirus.
ולא את הבן ולא את הבת, Velo es haben velo es habas,
so that's specific by the נרצע Nirtza as opposed to six years.
ולעולם, Le'olam, לעולמו של יובל, le'olamo shel Yovel, forever, meaning until the
יובל. Yovel. He also goes free during the יובל. Yovel. רמב"ם Rambam
points out that it's not that the דרשה drasha is לעולם le'olam
means לעולמו של יובל. le'olamo shel Yovel. That's what it's forced to
mean because of the פסוק, posuk, explicit פסוק posuk by יובל. Yovel.
That's how we know he goes free, because there's an explicit פסוק
posuk in בהר Behar that says he goes free when you have
the יובל. Yovel. Okay, so that's how we know the עבד עברי
Eved Ivri goes free in those two ways. Now we're going to
look at the idea of piercing the ear. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
מרצע. Marzea. Okay, you should pierce his ear with a מרצע, marzea,
a piercer, an awl, or something. אין לי אלא מרצע. Ein li
ela marzea. I only know an awl.
מניין לרבות הסול והסירה והמחט והמקדח? Minayin lerabbos hasol vehasira vehamachas vehamakdeach?
How do we know to include all of these things? Okay,
הסול hasol רש"י Rashi says is like a piece of wood. הסירה
hasira is a thorn. מחט machas is a
needle. והמקדח vehamakdeach is a I don't know some other type of
a piercing tool.
Okay. והמכתב Vehamichtav and something that presumably you would write through
like a stylus. How do we know all these things also work?
תלמוד לומר ולקחת. Talmud lomar velakachta.
And you shall take. Okay, לרבות כל דבר שייקח ביד. lerabbos kol
davar she'yikach beyad.
Anything that can be taken by the hand works, it doesn't have
to be המרצע, hamarzea, it doesn't have to be limited to המרצע.
hamarzea. It's not exactly clear what else פסוק posuk could have said,
maybe it should have started with the word המרצע hamarzea ולקחת. velakachta.
Anyway, somehow they're learning from that to be more inclusive. דברי רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda said. רבי אומר Rabbi omer מה
מרצע מיוחד של מתכת אף כל של מתכת. mah marzea meyuchad shel
mateses af kol shel mateses. The same way a מרצע marzea is
specifically of metal, אף כל של מתכת, af kol shel mateses, it
has to be metal. Some of the things mentioned above were wood,
that's not good, it has to be metal. Okay and we'll see
below what they're exactly debating, how broadly or expansively to read the
generalization of the פסוק. posuk. דבר אחר Davar acher המרצע hamarzea להביא
המרצע הגדול. lehavi hamarzea hagadol. The המרצע hamarzea to include even a
large מרצע. marzea. What exactly the point is about that, not exactly
clear, what is the big מרצע, marzea, also not clear. But anyway
we'll see about that in a minute. אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi
Elazar יודן בריבי. Yudan Beribbi. Said רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar יודן בריבי,
Yudan Beribbi, רש"י Rashi says that's the name of his place, בריבי
Beribbi means that he was a prestigious
personage. אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar יודן בריבי, Yudan Beribbi,
יודן, Yudan, this important personage by the name of
יודן, Yudan, היה דורש hayah doresh
כשהן רוצעין אין רוצעין אלא במילתא. kshe'hein rotzin ein rotzin ela bemilsa.
When they do the piercing, they do it in the lobe hanging
down from the ear, not in the actual, you know, sort of
skin of the ear itself, the cartilage or whatever, I don't know
the exact term. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim אין עבד עברי כהן נרצע
מפני שנעשה בעל מום. ein eved ivri kohen nirtza mipnei shena'asa ba'al
mum. The חכמים Chachamim disagree. They say and they're going to disagree
because we have a tradition. The tradition is that you don't pierce
the ear
of a כהן Kohen who's an עבד עברי Eved Ivri because you'll
make him a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay, now if that's the
tradition and we know that that's the הלכה, halacha, then that teaches
us that the hole is not made in the lobe, because if
you have a hole in the lobe, like you would do for
an earring, he wouldn't become a בעל מום. ba'al mum. It's only...
when it's in the actual sort of flesh of the ear itself.
So ואם תמצא לומר *ve'im timtza lomar* במילתא *bemilsa* האי *hai* מוציא
*motzei* מן *man* and if they do it in the lobe היכי
עבד עברי eved ivri כהן Kohen. נעשה בעל מום ba'al mum. *hechi
eved ivri kohen naaseh baal mum*? He wouldn't become a בעל מום
ba'al mum? *baal mum*. So since we have a teaching that you
don't do it for a כהן Kohen *kohen* because it would make
him a בעל מום ba'al mum, *baal mum*, then it must be
that you do it you know in the sort of the the
skin of the ear itself, not the lobe that hangs down. אין
רציעה אלא בגובה של אוזן *ein retzia ela begova shel ozen*, only
in the height of the ear. Okay, so that's that debate. Now
רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* says that that actually the
that a little bit plays off of the idea of המרצע ha'martze'a
*hamartzei'a*, the big this big awl, because even when a כהן Kohen,
*kohen* has a hole in his ear he's not a בעל מום
ba'al mum *baal mum* unless it's a certain size. So once we
introduce the idea of המרצע *hamartzei'a* that you can use a big
awl, so then that led to the statement that oh wait a
minute if it's a big awl that would make him a בעל
מום *baal mum*. How do you if it was a כהן Kohen,
*kohen* how do you deal with that? So the first response was
ר' אלעזר *Rebbi Elazar* said that this יודן ברבי Yudan be'Rabbi *Yudan
Berebbi* said oh okay then it must be since he has the
potential becoming a בעל מום *baal mum* since we mentioned this big
מרצע martze'a. *martzei'a* it must be that you do it in the
lobe of the ear. And the חכמים *chachamim* say no actually you
don't do it for a כהן Kohen *kohen* because he will be
a בעל מום *baal mum* and that proves that you do do
it in the place where he can become a בעל מום *baal
mum* you do do it in the ear itself. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to go back to the debate about
whether you can include wood or it has to be metal. במאי
קמיפלגי *Bemai kamifligi*? What is the debate of רבי Rabbi *Rebbi* and
the חכמים *chachamim*? That רבי *Rebbi* says that the you know that
רבי *Rebbi* says it has to be metal. רבי דורש כלל ופרט
*Rebbi doresh klal uprat*. רבי *Rebbi* adopts the hermeneutic principle of כלל
ופרט *klal uprat*. What's that principle? ולקחת velakachta, *Velakachta* כלל *klal*, מרצע
Martzei'a, *martzei'a* פרט prat, *prat*, באזנו ובדלת b'ozno u'vadelt, *beozno uvadelet* חזר
וכלל *chazar vechlal*. So ולקחת *Velakachta* is a general statement. Again, not
clear what else it could have said. מרצע *Martzei'a* is a specific.
באזנו ובדלת be'ozno ubadalet, *Beozno uvadelet*, the ear and the door, חזר
וכלל *chazar vechlal*, that's a general statement. Again I don't know how
it's a general statement it's not even talking about the object being
used but okay. כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal אי אתה דן
אלא כעין הפרט *Klal uprat vechlal iy ata dan ela ke'ein haprat*.
And the principle is general specific general though that leads you to
say that the real הלכה halacha *halacha* is anything similar to the
specific. כעין הפרט *Ke'ein haprat* similar to the specific. מה הפרט מפורש
של מתכת אף כל של מתכת *Ma haprat meforash shel matechet af
kol shel matechet*. And in the same way the awl is of
metal so therefore anything of metal. So how do we know metal
but only metal? Because the word you know מרצע *martzei'a* is a
metal is a metal piercing item and the כלל ופרט וכלל *klal
uprat vechlal* principle tells us to generalize it to similar similar meaning
of metal. Okay now the general way כלל ופרט וכלל *klal uprat
vechlal* works the following is that if you have just two כלל
ופרט *klal uprat* or פרט וכלל *prat uklal* you go by the
last one. כלל *Klal* is a general statement which would mean anything.
פרט *Prat* would is a is specific you're being פורט *poret* like
you're being identifying and listing I'm going to enumerate right that's what
פרט *prat* means לפרט *lepharet*. So therefore if I make a general
statement and then I'm specific in the end I'm left with the
specific thing. You know I say to my wife my wife tells
me to go to the store and buy something for dinner I
say what should I get? She says oh you know anything chicken.
Okay so then it means chicken you know she started being general
just get something for dinner what should I get? Chicken you know
get something for dinner chicken so you're left with the specification. Now
if it's the reverse order if it's פרט וכלל *prat uklal* then
you're left with the general.
Hey Dov would you go to the store get some chicken for
dinner? You know anything really anything's fine. So then you're left with
the more general you start with a specific but then you broaden
it. Okay it's only when you have כלל ופרט וכלל *klal uprat
vechlal* that you do כעין הפרט *ke'ein haprat*. You know what should
I get you know go get you know something for dinner what
should I get? Anything chicken anything. So by there I figure out
that like she doesn't want me to go ahead and get you
know we're not having a vegetarian dinner I could maybe get some
beef I could maybe maybe fish is a possibility but a כלל
*klal* and a פרט *prat* by themselves general specific you're left with
the second one whereas general specific general the message is similar to
the specific. That's the principle of כלל ופרט וכלל *klal uprat vechlal*
so it would have to be metal. Okay
that's the כלל ופרט וכלל *klal uprat vechlal* principle. Let's take a
look at the other approach. ר' יוסי דורש ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u'miut
*Rebbi Yossi doresh ribuy umiyut*. ר' יוסי *Rebbi Yossi*'s hermeneutic principle is
not general and specific it's expanding and contracting okay to to to
add or to to to limit to expand or to limit ריבוי
ומיעוט ribui u'miut, *ribuy umiyut*. ולקחת *Velakachta* ריבה *riba*, מרצע *martzei'a* מיעט
*miyet*, באזנו ובדלת be'ozno ubadalet, *beozno uvadelet* חזר וריבה chozar v'riba, *chazar
veriba*.
Obviously they look at the same words but the question is are
we calling it general and specific are we calling it expanding and
contracting? ריבוי מיעוט miut. וריבוי ריבה הכל *Ribuy miyut veribuy riba hakol*.
When you have a ריבוי מיעוט miut, וריבוי *ribuy miyut veribuy* when
you have this this expanding expanding, contracting, expanding, same thing as before,
but we're framing them differently, in the end you're left with pretty
much anything. מה ריבה? What do you include? ריבה כל מילי, Riba
kol mili, everything. מה מיעט? Ma miet? What do you exclude? מיעט
סם, Miet sam, using something that's not a piercing tool with like
through through pressure through a point, but you know burning it with
acid, that is completely different and therefore that's being excluded. So what
is the difference here for the hermeneutic principle? Because here we're not
looking at it as like general and specific, we're looking at it
as like expanding and contracting. If I say an expansive statement, anything,
it's anything. Then if I say no, chicken, okay, that's not I'm
not being specific about what I meant when I said anything. I'm
I'm limiting the scope, okay, it's a limiting word. I start with
everything and then I might limit it, so I'm limiting it to
say you know, chicken and things like chicken. That's using that example
as a way to contract that expansiveness. All right, but it's not
meant to be a specific, it's not a פרט, it's a מיעוט.
Again, same word just close in how you understand it. Okay, so
by the
time ריבוי ומיעוט gets you to where כלל ופרט וכלל gets you,
it's one step ahead. So by the time you get to the
מיעוט, chicken, you're already anything like chicken, which makes sense, why would
you have said an expansive and then a why would you have
said anything if you only meant chicken. So rather than seeing it
as an interpretation and a specification, what you have is you have
a contracting. So if it had just said ריבוי ומיעוט, ולקחת מרצע,
v'lakachta martze'a, I would have said okay, anything metal like מרצע. Then
it's
חזר וריבה, באזנו ובדלת, be'ozno ubadalet. that's expanding again, okay? So it's
like it's where expanding and really saying almost anything. So what is
the point of the contracting word? To say as long as it's
not totally different from this middle case. What would be totally different
from this? Something like acid, that would be totally different. But it
doesn't have to be similar to the middle because the middle isn't
a specification, the middle is only a contracting, expanding, contracting, expanding, you're
left with anything but what is most dissimilar. Okay. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi fine, so that's how you get that debate. That's an important
general two hermeneutic principles. Okay. Okay. רבי okay... now. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, המרצע להביא מרצע גדול. ha'martze'a l'havi martze'a gadol. מאי משמע? Mai
mashma? How do you know המרצע means the big one? כדאמר רבא,
K'damar Rava, הירך המיומנת שביירך. ha'yarech ha'miyumenet she'ba'yarech. So the same way
we say you know there's an approach that the גיד הנשה gid
ha'nasheh is only in the right thigh because it says אשר
כף הירך, asher kaf ha'yarech, so it means ה- ha the one,
the right one, the more important one, right hand is seen as
more important. So הכא נמי hacha nami המרצע המיוחד שבמרצעים ha'martze'a ha'miyuchad
she'ba'martza'im something big and important, significant, okay, I don't know they obviously
had some tool that they had in mind when they were referring
to this. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, יודן ברבי היה
דורש, Yudan be'Rabbi haya doresh, כשהן רוצעין אין רוצעין אלא במילתא, keshein
rotzin ein rotzin ela b'milta, they would only do it in the
in the lobe and that's how you would avoid בעל מום. וחכמים
אומרים אין עבד עברי כוהן נרצע מפני שנעשה בעל מום. V'Chachamim omrim
ein eved ivri kohen nirtza mipnei she'na'aseh ba'al mum. No, since the
הלכה halacha is you don't do it to a כוהן, kohen, it
proves that you don't do it in the lobe, you do it
higher up in the ear. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, ויעשה בעל
מום? v'ye'aseh ba'al mum? Where did that הלכה halacha come from? How
do you know that you don't let a כוהן kohen become a
בעל מום? You know there's an איסור issur to make a מום
בקדשים, mum b'kodashim, in sacrifices, but not for a כוהן kohen to
be a בעל מום, although it disqualifies him to make him to
do something that would make him a בעל מום although it would
disqualify him from העבודה. ha'avoda. ויעשה בעל מום? V'ye'aseh ba'al mum? אמר
רבה בר רב שילא אמר קרא, Amar Rabba bar Rav Shila amar
kra, ושב אל משפחתו, v'shav el mishpachto,
he shall return to his family, you know when he goes free
in the יובל. yovel. למוחזק שבמשפחתו, L'muchzak she'bi'mishpachto,
into his חזקה chazaka into the status that he had before. So
since this includes the עבד עברי eved ivri that is נרצע, nirtza,
right? That's the person who mostly would be I mean it's also
six years, but the sense you get in the פסוקים psukim by
the יובל yovel is somebody that was going to be working forever
and the יובל yovel came and freed him. Okay, so that's the
that's the עבד עברי eved ivri? that's נרצע nirtza and he goes
back to his status, it must be that if it's a כוהן
kohen that either if it's a כוהן kohen you don't do it
in the height of the ear, that's יודן ברבי's position or you
don't do it to a כוהן. kohen. Okay. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu,
עבד עברי כוהן מהו שימסור לו רבו שפחה כנענית? eved ivri kohen
mahu she'yimsor lo rabo shifcha knaanit? All right, now that we're talking
about a כוהן, kohen,
let and and that there might be some limitation, so this is
because of the דרשה drasha he has to go back to a
status. What about other are there other limitations in terms of his
behavior as an עבד עברי? eved Ivri, So we learn the principle
that you know it's in the תורה, Torah, אם אדוניו יתן לו
אשה, im adonav yiten lo isha, that his master can go ahead
and and give him a non-Jewish slave in order to produce babies.
Can he do it for a כוהן? kohen? Why not?
I mean, so so שפחה כנענית חידוש הוא, shifcha knaanit chiddush hu,
it's a חידוש chiddush that the תורה Torah allowed it, normally there
would be a prohibition for a man to have sex with a
non-Jewish slave specifically. specifically based on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of לא
יקדש ולא יקדשה *Lo yikadesh velo yikdesha*. Okay, so לא שנא כהנים
Kohanim ולא שנא ישראל Yisrael, *lo shna Kohanim velo shna Yisroel*. It
wouldn't matter, you know, once the תורה Torah *Torah*'s allowing it, this
overriding this איסור issur *issur* in this context, it wouldn't matter whether
it's a כהן kohen, *Kohen* or ישראל *Yisroel*. או דילמא שאני כהנים
דעברי בהו במצות יתירות *O dilma shani Kohanim d'ovrei be-mitzvos yeseros*? Maybe
כהנים *Kohanim* are different because they have extra מצות *mitzvos*, so therefore
maybe this is not allowed to כהנים *Kohanim*. Now, it's not just
they have extra מצות *mitzvos*, I think specifically it's that they have
things that more restrict the women that they can marry.
Interestingly, the emphasis of the תורה Torah *Torah* is not about having
sex, it's about being married to those women.
And here he's not exactly married to this שפחה כנענית shifcha Kna'anis
*Shifcha Kenaanis*, but it's a pseudo-marriage, and one could certainly imagine based
on ways חזל Chazal *Chazal* understand the general category of זונה zona
*Zona* that this woman would fall under the category of זונה zona
*Zona* as well. So it's not exactly a marriage, is she exactly
a זונה zona, *Zona* or not, she's not Jewish, so, you know,
the תורה Torah *Torah*'s talking
about when it's halachic קידושין *kiddushin* and so on, but it's very
close, so maybe that allowance wouldn't be made to a כהן Kohen,
*Kohen*. Okay. רב Rav אמר Amar, מותר muttar, *Rav amar mutar*, it's
permissible, ושמואל אמר אסור u'Shmuel amar assur. *u-Shmuel amar assur*, it's forbidden.
אמר ליה רב נחמן לרבנא *Amar lei Rav Nachman le-Ravanon*, said רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman* to רבנא *Ravanon*, כי הויתו בי מר שמואל Shmuel
*ki avisos be-bei Mar Shmuel* when you were in the house of
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, presumably רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* was one who had
told over this teaching of שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* or he was there
at the time. So he says באסקומדרי איטטליתו *be-is kamderi itatlisos*, you
must have been playing with cards. Okay, you must have been on
your iPhones. Okay, that's רשי Rashi *Rashi* says it means cards, the
ערוך *Aruch* says it means like you were playing with the puppies
or something. Like, you must have been distracted. You weren't paying attention
because it can't be that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* said it, or שמואל
*Shmuel* said it he should have been challenged. Why? מאי טעמא *Mai
ta'ama*? מאי טעמא לא תימרו ליה *Mai ta'ama lo teimu lei*, why
didn't you say back to שמואל *Shmuel* מהא *me-ha*? That שמואל *Shmuel*
can't be right that that it's forbidden to כהנים *Kohanim*. How do
you know? דחכמים אומרים אין עבד עברי eved Ivri, כהן Kohen נרצע
nirtza מפני שנעשה בעל מום *De-chachamim omrim ein eved Ivri Kohen nirza
mipnei she-na'asa ba'al mum*. That you don't do a כהן Kohen *Kohen*,
an עבד עברי eved Ivri *eved Ivri* who's a כהן Kohen *Kohen*
isn't נרצע nirtza, *nirza* because it'll make him a בעל מום *ba'al
mum*. ואם תאמר אין רבו מוסרו לו שפחה Shiphcha, כנענית *Ve-im tomar
ein rabo mosro lo shifcha kenaanis*, but if we were to hold
that an עבד Eved. עברי *eved Ivri* כהן Kohen *Kohen* would not
be able to have a שפחה כנענית *shifcha kenaanis* and that would
even be during the first six years,
תיפוק ליה דבעינא אהבתי את אדוני את אשתי ואת בני ahavti et
adoni et ishti v'et banai וליכא v'leika. *teipokei lei de-be'ina ahavti es
adoni es ishti ve-es banai ve-leika*, because you have to do it
the way the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* says, and as we're going to
see, an עבד eved, עברי *eved Ivri* cannot choose to be a
נרצע nirtza *nirza* unless he actually was given this slave woman and
had children with them and therefore would allow him to say אהבתי
את אשתי ahavti es ishti, ואת בני *ahavti es ishti ve-es banai*.
So therefore, since the only reason a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* is excluded
from being נרצע nirtza. *nirza* is because of the בעל מום *ba'al
mum* issue, it proves that the other thing could happen to him
and therefore he can be given a female slave to have children
with. Okay, וותו לא מידי *ve-su lo midi*, and וותו לא מידי
*su lo midi*, end of discussion. There is nothing more to be
said. It is clearly שמואל *Shmuel*'s position is wrong, and therefore, yes,
a כהן *Kohen* can get a שפחה כנענית *shifcha kenaanis*. Okay, איבעיא
להו *ibaya lehu*, now they ask, once we're on this roll, we're
going to ask another question, go a little off-topic. מהו ביפת תואר
*Ma b'yefas toar*? כהן מהו ביפת תואר *Kohen ma b'yefas toar*? Can
a כהן *Kohen* who goes out to war, interesting that the כהנים
*Kohanim* are going out to war, can he go ahead, maybe he's
the כהן המשיח מלחמה *Kohen mashuach milchama*, anyway, can he go ahead
and take a יפת תואר yefas to'ar *yefas toar*?
You know, it's interesting, יפת תואר yefas to'ar. *yefas toar* the woman
that's taken captive in war, the beautiful woman that the man desires.
So, again, this is interesting question. Are we assuming כהנים *Kohanim* are
going out to war? You know, the תורה Torah *Torah* says, you
know, that חלק לא יהיה בתוכם *cheilek lo yihiye be-socham*, they don't
have a חלק *cheilek* in the ביזה *biza*. Are they entitled to
take women to take captives, to take booty? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
somehow assumes that's not a problem. Okay, and wants to know does
the תורה Torah *Torah* allow יפת תואר Yefas to'ar, *yefas toar*?
So מהו ביפת תואר *ma b'yefas toar*? חידוש הוא *Chidush hu*, it's
a חידוש *chidush* that the תורה Torah *Torah* allowed this. לא שנא
כהן ולא שנא ישראל *Lo shna Kohen ve-lo shna Yisroel*, it doesn't
matter כהן *Kohen* or ישראל *Yisroel*. או דילמא שאני כהנים דעברי בהו
במצות יתירות *O dilma shani Kohanim d'ovrei be-mitzvos yeseros*? Or maybe כהנים
*Kohanim* are different because they have extra מצות *mitzvos*. Now, we're going
to see in a well, let's read a little bit further. Okay,
and again, specifically מצות *mitzvos* that have to do with the women
that they can marry and have sex with. רב אמר מותר ושמואל
אמר אסור Rav amar mutar u'Shmuel amar assur. *Rav amar mutar u-Shmuel
amar assur*. רב *Rav* says it's permissible and שמואל *Shmuel* says it's
forbidden. ביאה ראשונה bi'ah rishonah. דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי *Bi'ah rishona
de-chulei alma lo peligi de-shari*. The when it comes to having sex
the first time with this woman, everybody agrees it's permissible. דלא דברה
תורה Torah אלא כנגד יצר הרע yetzer hara, *De-lo dibra Torah ela
keneged yetzer hara*. The תורה Torah *Torah*, why did the תורה *Torah*
allow this? Because the תורה *Torah* knew that, I mean, it's obviously
an immoral act and it's go violates, you know, other principles in
the תורה *Torah*, you know, we'll discuss in a minute what מצות
*mitzvos* it goes against and so on, but clearly it's not something
that normally would be allowed, also because it says יפת תואר yifat
to'ar *yefas toar*, beautiful, right? It clearly means that it's speaking to
the fact that this person is feeling a lust and a desire.
So this is a concession. Since it's a concession and not something
that's like לכתחילה *lechatchila* by any means, so therefore, you know, if
people if men are at war, they have this lust and desire
and the תורה *Torah* has to give them a maybe that concession,
of course we're completely ignoring here the woman who's being raped and
so on and all of that, we'll get to that in a
minute, anyway, so clearly the תורה would have to give that concession
to כהנים as well. If it's gonna allow to ישראל, it's gonna
allow to כהן. It's the lust of the moment. You can't make
a distinction there. Okay.
לא דיברה תורה אלא כנגד יצר הרע. Lo dibrah Torah ela keneged
yetzer hara. כי פליגי בביאה שנייה. Ki pligi b'via sheniya. What the
debate is about the second act of sex, I'll also discuss in
a minute first act and second act. רב אמר מותר muttar ושמואל
אמר U'Shmuel amar, אסור. assur. Rav says it's permissible, Shmuel says it's
forbidden. רב אמר מותר הוא ואישתרי אישתרי. Rav amar mutar ho v'ishtarei
ishtarei. Rav says it's permitted since it was permitted, it was permitted.
The first time was permitted, so therefore the תורה is saying this
whole הלכה halachah applies to a כהן as well. ושמואל אמר אסור.
assur Shmuel says it's forbidden. Why? דהויא לה גיורת. de'hava la giyores.
Because by the second time, that's when after he brought her home
and did this whole process and she cried for her parents and
she realized she was not going to see her people again, and
the way חז"ל Chazal understand what happens there is that she's convert.
She's, I mean she's forced to convert but she converts. Okay. And
once she converts, וגיורת לכהן לא חזיא, v'giyores le'kohen lo chazya, then
it's not permitting whatever was the יפת תואר problem. Then it specifically
falls into the category of what the תורה אסר assar to a
כהן, which is a גיורת, giyores, which is what חז"ל Chazal understood
זונה was גיורת. giyores. Okay, and that was a, גיורת giyores is,
whatever. I mean a זונה is a זונה, but also גיורת giyores
is in that category. That's a whole very sensitive and difficult topic.
We're going to bracket that, this is difficult enough as it is
right now. Okay, but anyway שמואל says so whatever the תורה allowed,
it allowed from the יפת תואר. And now this woman after she
converts would have a straight on איסור issur of גיורת, giyores, and
therefore the תורה never made that permissible, and therefore she remains forbidden.
Okay. Now, what is this
in terms of the first and the second act of sex? So
it seems very clear, although I'll mention, I'll discuss a debate in
a second, that, but it seems very clear that what it means
is at the moment of war, okay, that that's stage number one,
and the man sees and he lusts and the תורה allows him
to have sex with her, rape her essentially against her will.
And, and yeah, what's being focused on here is his sin, not
the act of rape, and it's extremely problematic and I have nothing
to say about that.
But at least the תורה tempers it, the violence done to her
and all of that, by saying he doesn't take her as a
sexual slave. If he wants then to keep her, then he has
to go through this process, has to,
she becomes part, he marries her, she becomes part of the household.
Again, she doesn't have a say in that. Forced to convert against
her will and so on, but it is significantly different than what
used to be, which was just raping women on the battlefield and
then taking them as sexual slaves. So, those are the two stages,
stage one and stage two, and again there is nothing to say
about the fact
that the גמרא Gemara's is a, that that rape is going on
here and what the impact of that on the woman and how
that is not being looked at. Okay. Now,
part of this ambiguity, right, is that it says the פסוק pasuk
says וראית בשביה אשת יפת תואר V'raita bashivyah eshes yefas to'ar וחשקת
בה, v'chashakta bah, you desire, ולקחת לך לאשה, v'lakachta lecha l'ishah, take
her as a wife, והבאתה אל תוך ביתך, v'heveisa el toch beisecha,
take her into your house, do this whole process, ואחר כן תבוא
אליה ובעלתה, v'achar ken tavo eleha u'vealtah, and afterwards
you can have sex with her. So if you actually think about
it, the פסוקים psukim sound like no sex happens right there. Sex
happens after the whole process. I mean ולקחת לך לאשה v'lakachta lecha
l'ishah there doesn't mean, presumably doesn't mean take her,
it means take her to be your wife and then this is
the whole process you're going to have to go through. Okay. But
somehow חז"ל understand that because לא דיברה תורה אלא כנגד יצר הרע
Lo dibrah Torah ela keneged yetzer hara that and there's וחשקת בה
v'chashakta bah the lust, the desire, it has to be that ולקחת
לך לאשה v'lakachta lecha l'ishah or whatever, I don't know where they're
seeing in the פסוק, pasuk but somehow even before והבאתה אל תוך
ביתך v'heveisa el toch beisecha there's going to be that first ביאה
ראשונה. beiah rishonah. So,
according to this debate, they both say it has to be allowed
to the כהן, but they're debating afterwards. רב says that once she
was allowed, allowed, the איסור issur. of גיורת giyores is being bracketed.
And שמואל says, no, then she falls into a new category, total
אסור. assur We'll read another version of this debate and then I
want to sort of discuss רש"י's Rashi, position. So the גמרא Gemara,
says like this: איכא
דאמרי Ika d'amri others say, בביאה שנייה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסירא
דהויא לה גיורת B'via sheniya kulei alma lo pligi de'asira de'hava la
giyores everybody agrees after the whole process or whatever she's forbidden because
she's a גיורת, giyores, so the כהן does not have the option
of taking her home and making her his wife. כי פליגי בביאה
ראשונה Ki pligi b'via rishonah the debate is the first act of
sex. רב אמר מותר דהא לא דיברה תורה אלא כנגד יצר הרע
Rav amar mutar de'ha lo dibrah Torah ela keneged yetzer hara Rav
says look the תורה is waving the איסור. issur so it will
also waive the איסור issur that applies to a כהן, and שמואל,
and therefore, you know, there's no real difference in the ביאה ראשונה.
Biah Rishonah She's not a גיורת, giyores, it's not marriage. ושמואל אמר,
and שמואל says כל היכא דלא קרינן ביה ואתית אל תוך ביתך
לא קרינן ביה וראית בשביה. kol heicha d'lo karinan beih v'ayseisa el
toch beisecha lo karinan beih v'raisa bashivyah. No,
any woman for whom the whole process isn't allowed, that she cannot
end up into marriage, we don't, the Torah never allowed the first
act of sex to begin with. Okay. Now what's not been explained
is what exact איסור issur, is the Torah permitting. You know, again,
it's rape, it's horrific, it's violence against the woman. But you know
from the גמרא's Gemara perspective of the הלכות halachos here,
you know, we had a, you know, is there a prohibition of
having sex with a non-Jewish woman? The Torah speaks about לא תתחתן
בם, lo sis'chasen bam, which is about intermarriage and it's specifically in
the context they're talking about the seven כנעני Kena'ani nations. You know,
there's a whole discussion in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah about what is
the nature of, you know, sex with a non-Jewish woman, although based
on the story of פנחס Pinchas definitely there's the point about קנאים
פוגעים בו, kana'im pog'im bo, that in public, which is presumably, you
know, the case here, even non-marriage context, any non-Jewish woman it would
be a case of קנאים פוגעים בו, kana'im pog'im bo, it would
clearly be אסור assur. in the Torah. So it's an interesting discussion
and it gets discussed at length in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and
elsewhere about the nature of the איסור, issur, but there's understood that
clearly there's going to be an איסור, issur you know, of sex
with this non-Jewish woman besides the fact that it's rape and that
the Torah is allowing. But let's see now in terms of exactly
the nature of the איסור issur gets whatever problematized or referred to
with this next line. So let's take a look. And then we're
going to go back to the issue of first sex and second
sex. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. וראית בשביה. V'raisa bashivyah. You shall
see in captivity.
בשעת שביה. Besha'as shivyah. So at the time of captivity, which again
according to,
you know, the simple reading of the גמרא, Gemara that the first
act of sex is on the battlefield. So that's what בשעת שביה
besha'as shivyah means, that it has to be like at that moment,
you know, that's that first act of sex at that moment. רש"י,
Rashi if you look at רש"י Rashi first wide line at the
bottom, אם נתן מתחלה עיניו בה ולא שלקחה למכור לשפחה ואחר כך
נתן עיניו בה. im nasan mitechilah einav bah v'lo shelakachah limkor l'shifchah
v'achar kach nasan einav bah. So רש"י Rashi says we're not talking
about sex, it means that at that moment of the battle and
of captivity, immediately at that moment, that's when the guy said, ah,
I want her, I want to have sex with her, I want
her for my wife. That's how that whole process begins, not first
he took her as a slave and then the desire came later.
Okay. אשת, Eishes, a wife. ואפילו אשת איש, v'afilu eishes ish, even
if she's married to a, even if she's married. Now
this is interesting because normally הלכה halachah does not recognize, meaning for
non-Jews, one of the שבע מצות בני נח sheva mitzvos bnei Noach
is adultery. ודבק באשתו ולא באשת חברו. v'davak b'ishto v'lo b'eishes chaveiro.
However, in other areas it's clear that vis-a-vis the status for Jews,
we don't recognize the institution of marriage that exists amongst non-Jews and
she does not have a status of a married woman. So why
they would have to say אשת איש eishes ish is funny because
it doesn't make her more forbidden to Jews. So there's two interesting
answers to that. One is תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos actually says no,
the פסוק pasuk that says ודבק באשתו ולא באשת חברו v'davak b'ishto
v'lo b'eishes chaveiro is actually applies to Jews as well and therefore
even though it's not the איסור issur of לא תנאף, lo sin'af,
the איסור issur, of adultery which is punishable by stoning, if a
Jewish man had sex with a non-Jewish woman married who was married
to a non-Jewish man, that would be a violation of ודבק באשתו
ולא באשת חברו. v'davak b'ishto v'lo b'eishes chaveiro. That's what תוספות Tosafos
says and the Torah is permitting it here. רמב"ן Ramban says it's
not about איסור, issur. I mean a technical איסור. issur? רמב"ן Ramban
says it's still even more מכוער הדבר, mechuar hadavar, you know, it's
even more disgusting to be doing this, to be taking her and
taking her basically forcing, you know, raping her, taking her away from
her household, her husband, it's even more disgusting if, you know, she's
married. And especially because he goes on to say the process is
to get her to cry and abandon her household and so on
and
to resign herself to her fate and to be finally to be
your wife, and it remains, and you know, and she's even more
problematic if she's always, if she's thinking about her first husband. So
and nevertheless the Torah allows it.
יפת תואר, a beautiful woman. לא דברה תורה אלא כנגד יצר הרע.
Lo dibrah Torah ela keneged yetzer hara. This is where we have
the idea that this is a concession other than hopefully we would
think that anyway, but because it speaks about how beautiful she is
and the הלכה is she doesn't have to be beautiful, it just
has to be you want her, you this man want her, but
it's describing her as this to explain to you that there's this
יצר הרע, you know, that's וחשקת בה v'chashakta bah that has to
somehow be given some type of an outlet. Okay. Now here we
get to the tricky part.
מוטב שיאכלו ישראל בשר תמותות שחוטות ואל יאכלו בשר תמותות נבילות. Mutav
she'yochlu Yisrael b'sar temutos shechutos v'al yochlu b'sar temutos neveilos. Better that
Jews should eat, you know, meat that's going to die but was
slaughtered properly and let them not eat meat that's going to die
and died of natural causes. meat that was from a deathly cow,
a cow that was about was in the process of dying, but
at least you שחט shechted it before it died, so it was
very problematic, it was very close to being אסור because, you know,
if it had died it would be a נבילה, nevelah, but you
made it technically מותר, muttar so nobody is happy with that situation.
Also probably not too healthy.
But okay, better you should do that than to eat the meat
that it actually died and became a נבילה, nevelah, which basically means
that we have to somehow, it's sometimes the choice, you know, it's
between, you know, it's between two bad options. Better to do something
that is, that is, you know,
unseemly, even despicable, even whatever, but at least it's on this side
of being מותר muttar rather than being on the other side of
being אסור. And this actually is a line, now at the top
of כ"ב עמוד א' chaf bet amud aleph I should have said,
this actually is a line that is used sometimes in פוסקים, poskim,
you know, to make their peace with less than ideal situations because
the alternative is even worse. Now, the question is what would have
been the, what would have been the איסור? issur Meaning, how is
it more מותר than what the alternative would have been?
So רמב"ן Ramban says that the איסור issur that the Torah, I
mean what's the איסור issur that the Torah is protecting us from,
you know, that would have been even worse? So the רמב"ן Ramban
says the איסור that the Torah is protecting us from is that
the man would have basically decided to have, you know, kept her
and married her as a non-Jew, not gone through this whole גיורות
giyurus process, you know, or kept on sleeping with her, with or
without marriage, and that would have been a violation of לא תתחתן
בם. lo titchaten bam. You know, the פסוק pasuk says וחשקת בה
ולקחת לך לאשה, vachashakta bah velakachta lecha le'ishah, so it sounds like
the man actually wants to marry her, not just have that first
act of sex. Okay. So therefore the Torah is allowing it, not
through, again it's not concerned with right here with the woman and
what it's doing to the woman. The Torah is allowing it to
do it by making her a גיורת, giyoret, maybe against her, her
will, but going through a process that makes her גיורת giyoret and
therefore that's like, you know, excuse the analogy but the part about
making a שחט shechting the cow that's dying. All right, like, you
know, it almost whatever, you saved her at the last minute because
you made her a גיורת. giyoret. Like you forced the גיורות giyurus
on her but you made her a גיורת giyoret and now you're
going to have be able to do it in an in a
היתר hetter way, rather than being married to her as a non-Jew.
Now how about that first act of sex? Okay, the first act
of sex also is a little bit more כשר kosher because it's
part of this process of being married to her in a היתר
hetter way and not about a, you know, a, being married to
her as a non-Jew. Anyway, that's how the Torah made it a
little bit more on this side of being מותר than on the
other side. Okay, that is, that's that. Now we're going to get
to, I promised we'd get back to this question of first act
of sex and second act because I'm going to reframe it in
a minute. Okay, and let's continue. וחשקת, vachashakta, and you desire, אף
על פי שאינה נאה, af al pi she'eina nava, right, it doesn't
have to be יפת תואר as long as this man desires her.
בה ולא בחברתה, bah velo bachaverta, not her and her friend, it
only allows it with one woman. ולקחת, ליקוחין יש לך בה, likuchin
yesh lecha bah, you actually will be halakhically married because
she'll be converted and then the marriage will be תופס. tofes. לך
לאשה, lecha le'ishah, for you for wife, שלא יקח שתי נשים, אחת
לו ואחת לאביו, אחת לו ואחת לבנו, shelo yikach shetei nashim, achat
lo ve'achat le'aviv, achat lo ve'achat livno, that you can't take two,
one for you and one for your son or one for your
father. It's really not about two, it's really about it's only for
your desire and not for somebody else. והבאתה, ve'aveitah, bring her, and
here becomes this keyword that makes us go back and question first
sex versus second sex. Okay, מלמד שלא ילחצנה במלחמה. melamed shelo yichtzenah
bamilchamah. He should not force her, the word ילחצנה yichtzenah is almost
like press her, in war. Now, what does that mean? So the
simple sense of that is don't rape her in war. Wait till
you get her back into the house, which is what it sounds
like in the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, and that is what רש"י Rashi
says.
Get back to רש"י Rashi in a minute, that's against everything we've
been saying. But just for a second, for those who have been
saying that no, he does have sex with her, you know, before
he takes her home and then takes her home, goes through this
process and then after that whole process, then finally that's the second
sex is after she converts and then they're husband and wife, a
clear difference between before and after,
what is this לא ילחצנה במלחמה? lo yichtzenah bamilchamah? So there's a
range of interpretations.
תוספות Tosafot says one is don't start the process of the 30
days or whatever, that doesn't, that's not a good, a good read
at all. רמב"ן Ramban has a couple of possibilities. Number one is
some this some others. Number one is don't do it there in
the battlefield,
go and, this is רמב"ם Rambam actually, you know, go do it
somewhere, take her somewhere into the town, don't do it out in
the battlefield,
במלחמה. bamilchamah. So it's still the before and after she converts, but
it's not there in the battlefield.
That's interesting, a little better and a little worse. It's a little
better in the sense that, you know, it waits for the lust
to abate. So if he first takes her home, maybe by the
time he gets home he'll decide he doesn't want her as a
wife and after, you know, go through this whole process and won't
even have that sex the first time. So you sort of understand
if you say that they have to wait to take her home,
you understand that maybe actually this will all turn out okay for
this woman. On the other hand, you know, once he has taken
her home and his lust has abated, why is the Torah letting
him have sex with her against her will and before she converted?
So
it's
a little better and a little worse if you say that he
has to wait until he takes her home even for that first
sex, but I actually think in the balance makes it better because
maybe therefore he'll calm down and not being raped in the battlefield.
The רא"ם Re'em has a really interesting explanation. He says that
you can't force her, that the Torah allowed this first act of
sex only if
she consents. Now, one could ask how much consent is it a
woman taken captive in the battlefield and so on, okay, but at
least, you know, it's not an act of violent rape and it
really has to be that she has to say that she's okay
with this. So that's quite fascinating, that's really important that it takes
that first—either it's with her... the sex is going to happen either
with her consent at the battlefield or after this גירות Geirus process,
which she doesn't have a say in but nevertheless, right, makes it
all a little bit more manageable. Okay, still horrific but a little
bit more manageable. Okay, so those are various explanations of לא יחצנה
במלחמה. Lo Yechatzenah bamilchama. And one other is that it's only once,
it can't be more than once. Okay, let's go back to רש"י
Rashi, who reads it as, you know, wait till after the whole
process and only then have sex with her. So for רש"י, Rashi
no raping, no sex in the battlefield, none when she comes home,
everything only happens after the whole process has happened. And according to
that, you know, a, really gives him time to calm down, a
whole month, and that makes it much, much better in a way
that's the simple sense of the פסוקים. Pesukim. What about the big
distinction the גמרא Gemara made between ביאה ראשונה Biah Rishonah and ביאה
שנייה? Biah Shniyah? It's not like it's before and after the גירות,
Geirus, they're both after the
גירות. Geirus. So according to this read it would only be that,
you know, that the point is, yes, הלכתית Halachically it's the exact
same, it's after the גירות, Geirus, but since דברה תורה כנגד יצר
הרע, Dibra Torah keneged yetzer hara, there was a thinking maybe that
for the כהן, remember, this was all framed in terms of the
כהן distinguishing between ביאה ראשונה and ביאה שנייה, Biah Shniyah, that maybe
the Torah would have allowed it once, but not as an ongoing
thing, especially if you understand, right, for the כהן the emphasis is
not to marry. אשה גרושה לא יקחו, Isha gerusha lo yikachu, זונה
וחללה לא יקחו. Zona vachallala lo yikachu. So according to that, it's
really not significant at all, first or second, it's just maybe there
would have been an allowance for a כהן just once, but basically
no sex, no anything until after the whole process. So that actually
is a more פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Pesukim and makes it
much more manageable what's happening here.
Again, it's still that she's being forced to convert against her will,
but considering that people would rape women on the battlefield, take women
as sexual slaves, the Torah says if you want her, it has
to be a wife and it has to go through this process.
Okay, and in the end the ירושלמי Yerushalmi brings down exactly both
of these two opinions, which in our גמרא Gemara is רש"י Rashi
versus the other ראשונים. Rishonim. All right, now we go back, remember
we were talking about an עבד. eved, All of this was a
digression because of an עבד כהן Eved Kohen and about whether he
would be allowed to have a שפחה, which the answer was yes,
is he allowed אשת יפת תואר, Eshet Yefat To'ar, that's a debate.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, five lines from the top of כב עמוד
א. Kaf Bet Amud Aleph.
אמר יאמר העבד, Amar Yomar Ha'Eved, now we're dealing with this idea
of the מרצע, of the piercing with the awl. עד שיאמר וישנה,
Ad sheyomar v'yishneh, he has to say it twice, אמר יאמר, Amar
Yomar, that he wants to stay. אמר בתחילת שש ולא אמר בסוף
שש, Amar bitchilat shesh v'lo amar besof shesh, אינו נרצע. Eino nirtza.
If he says at the beginning of the six years and not
at the end, then that's not going to work. שנאמר, Shenemar, now
רש"י Rashi says you would just say it wouldn't work because we
just said he has to say it twice, but רש"י Rashi says
even if he says twice at the beginning and twice at the
end, it won't work. Why? שנאמר לא אצא חופשי, Shenemar lo etzei
chofshi, עד שיאמר בשעת יציאה. Ad sheyomar b'sha'at yetziah. I don't want
to go free, so clearly it's talking about the end of the
six years. All right. אמר בסוף שש ולא אמר בתחילת שש, Amar
besof shesh v'lo amar bitchilat shesh, אינו נרצע. Eino nirtza.
Now, if he says at the end and not at the beginning,
that also doesn't work. Why not? שנאמר אמר יאמר העבד, Shenemar amar
yomar ha'eved, עד שיאמר כשהוא עבד. Ad sheyomar k'shehu eved. He still
has to be a slave. Now you're all saying he is still
a slave, it's just at the end, so the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that. Okay. אמר, let's unpack this. אמר בתחילת שש
ולא אמר בסוף שש, Amar bitchilat shesh v'lo amar besof shesh, אינו
נרצע. Eino nirtza. נרצע nirtza, שנאמר shene'emar לא אצא חופשי. lo eitzei
chafshi. Okay, so if he says at the beginning not at the
end, it's because it says it's not good because the תורה says
לא אצא חופשי lo eitzei chafshi and he has to be on
the verge of going free.
I just lost my place. לא אצא חופשי. lo eitzei chafshi. מאי
אירייא Mai irya לא אצא חופשי? lo eitzei chafshi? Why, how should
that be the only problem with saying it at the beginning of
the sixth years? תיפוק ליה דבעינן teipuk lei d'ba'inan אהבתי את אדוני
את אשתי ואת בני ahavti et adoni et ishti v'et banai. וליכא.
v'leika. If it's ממש mamash at the beginning, you know, we just
said before about the כהן or whatever, like he has to already
have been given a wife, you know, a non-Jewish slave, he has
to have had kids with them, so clearly this procedure, this process
can't begin at the beginning of the sixth years.
So
וליכא. ותו אמר בסוף ולא אמר בתחילת שש אינו נרצע. V'su amar
b'sof v'lo amar b'techilas shesh eino nirtza. The explanation why it doesn't
work to say it at the end, שנאמר shene'emar העבד, ha'eved,
because he has to still be a slave. אטו Atu סוף שש
לאו עבד הוא? sof shesh lav eved hu? What does that mean?
It's the end of the six years, he's still a slave. And
that's really the key to understanding this ברייתא. Braita. It shows you
that when it says at the end, it means really after the
slave, after the whole עבדות avdus is done, after the six years.
So the beginning means before the עבדות avdus is done and that's
how רבא Rava is going to explain it. אמר רבא Amar Rava
בתחילת פרוטה אחרונה בסוף פרוטה אחרונה. b'techilas pruta achrona b'sof pruta achrona.
It means have we gotten up to the last penny or not.
Let's say you figure out
based on how much his value was or whatever, he, this slave
was basically bought at the cost of a penny an hour.
Okay, so in that last hour, that last hour of the six
years, once you enter that last hour, he is technically still a
slave but there's no, you know, it's like less than a פרוטה's
pruta worth, right, there's no like monetary money that he actually
owed, he still owes to his master. So it's like this interesting
in-between period. So during that last hour, right, he can't say it
because it doesn't satisfy עד שהוא עבד. ad shehu eved. He's not
fully a slave in the sense that his master doesn't have an
actual money claim, something worth more than a פרוטה pruta against him.
All right, so obviously after the whole six is done, he obviously
can't say it, he's no longer an עבד, eved, but even in
that last hour, he can't say it. Okay,
so wait. Now, how about not the beginning of six? It means
anytime up to that last hour. Now you are two hours away
from him being freed, so let him say it now. Okay, now
he's still fully an עבד, eved there's like more than a penny,
you know, more than a פרוטה pruta that his master has against
him. So no, that doesn't work
because he's not close enough to going free. So he's העבד ha'eved
but he's not in the category of לא אצא חופשי, lo eitzei
chafshi, which means he's at literally the cusp of going free. So
in order to satisfy both, he has to say it before the
last hour's over, okay, where he's still fully העבד ha'eved after he
has אשה ובנים. isha u'banim. I don't know if he has to
say it the last day, he could say it anytime once he
has אשה ובנים. isha u'banim. Okay, then he's saying it as an
עבד, and then he has to say it within the last hour,
within the last פרוטה, pruta, because then he is maybe not an
עבד but he's still at the cusp of going free and it's
the לא אצא חופשי. lo eitzei chafshi. Okay, so you got to
time it perfectly. All right. And one wonders, you know, again if
this is being done here, you know, this being making it so
specific, making it a little bit harder to be a נרצע, nirtza?
which the גמרא was not happy with that choice of being a
נרצע nirtza. as we'll see. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan לו אשה ובנים
ולרבו אין אשה ובנים lo isha u'banim u'l'rabo ein isha u'banim and
now we're going to see a whole other new set of criteria
that's going to make it harder for him to be a נרצע.
If he was given a wife, you know, if he has a
wife and children, meaning this שפחה כנענית and the slaves that were
born from it, and his master does not, אינו נרצע. eino nirtza.
Then you can't do this process נרצע, שנאמר shene'emar כי אהבך ואת
ביתך. ki ahevcha v'et beisecha. I love you and your household, so
there has to be a household. Sometimes household is only understood to
be wife, but here it's wife and children parallel to him. לרבו
אשה ובנים ולו אין אשה ובנים, L'rabo isha u'banim v'lo ein isha
u'banim, let's say his master has and he doesn't, אינו נרצע, eino
nirtza, שנאמר shene'emar אהבתי את אדוני את אשתי ואת בני. es ishti
ve'es banai, He has to be able to say I love my
wife and my children, and that's exactly why we proved that even
a כהן, this would apply, would be able to have this non-Jewish
slave as a wife. הוא אוהב את רבו ורבו אינו אוהבו, Hu
ohev et rabo v'rabo eino ohavo, he loves his master and his
master doesn't love him, אינו נרצע, eino nirtza, you can't do this
process, שנאמר כי טוב לו עמך, shene'emar ki tov lo imach, because
it is good to him, now, it is good to him
with
you, so meaning it's good for him but
it has to be reciprocal, it has to also be good for
you.
רבו אוהבו, Rabo ohavo, the master loves him. והוא אינו אוהב את
רבו, vehu eino ohev es rabo, he doesn't love his master, אינו
נרצע שנאמר כי אהבך, eino nirtza shene'emar ki ahevcha, he loves you.
Now you might be asking, if he doesn't like his master, why
is he wanting to stay a נרצע? But there could be a
lot of reasons, you know, like he says, אהבתי את אשתי, you
know, את אשתי ואת בני, and maybe he doesn't have any prospects
out in the larger world, maybe he has a, you know, it's
better for him for a whole range of reasons, financial and other
reasons. But if he can't say כי אהבך, ki ahevcha, right,
you know,
he loves you, if he doesn't have a good relationship with his
master, then he cannot do the נרצע. הוא חולה ורבו אינו חולה,
hu choleh verabo eino choleh, he is sick and his master is
not sick, אינו נרצע, eino nirtza, can't do it, שנאמר shene'emar כי
טוב לו עמך, ki tov lo imach, it has to be good,
and it's not good right now because he's sick. So presumably, so
it all depends on that last day, right? Is he going to
be sick? Because now he's made it a very specific time, he
has to be able to say this.
רבו חולה והוא אינו חולה, rabo choleh vehu eino choleh, his master
is sick and he's not. So again, presumably at the time when
he is saying this, which we now at least know there's one
specific time, that last hour, that last פרוטה prutah it has to
say, אינו נרצע, eino nirtza, שנאמר, shene'emar, can't do it, עמך, imach,
it has to be good with him with you, so meaning for
you also you have to be good, you have to be healthy.
בעי רב ביבי בר אביי, ba'ei Rav Bibi bar Abaye, שניהם חולים
מהי, sheneihem cholim mai, let's say they're both sick. עמך בעינן, imach
ba'inan, is the emphasis on עמך, imach, they have to be equal?
והאיכא, ve'ika, and you have it here. או דלמא כי טוב לו,
o dilma ki tov lo, it's good, and טוב tov is meaning
not sick, so עמך בעינן. imach ba'inan. והא ליכא, veha lika, and
you don't have it. תיקו, teiku, we leave that as a question.
Not exactly sure about that because it's still not true כי טוב
לו, ki tov lo, and that's where we presumably learned out that
he can't be a חולה. choleh. Anyway, fine.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, כי טוב לו עמך, ki tov lo imach,
עמך במאכל, imach bema'achal, this is a famous גמרא that we've quoted
before. Okay, he has to be with you, you have to treat
him equally in food, עמך במשתה, imach bemishte, drink, you know, you
have to treat, give him equal accommodations. שלא תהא אתה אוכל פת
נקיה, shelo tehei atah ochel pas nekiyah, you can't eat white bread,
והוא אוכל פת קיבר, vehu ochel pas kivar, and he eats bran
bread. אתה שותה יין ישן, atah shoseh yayin yashan, you drink nice
aged wine, והוא שותה יין חדש, vehu shoseh yayin chadash,
and he drinks the newer wine, doesn't taste as good. Literally, you
have to give him all the accommodations you take for yourself. אתה
ישן על גבי מוכין, atah yashen al gabei mochin, you have a
nice feather bed, of, you know, silk, you know, והוא ישן על
גבי תבן, vehu yashen al gabei teven, and he sleeps on straw.
So you have to give him exactly equal accommodations. I mean, this
is going to be a high disincentive for anybody to get an
עבד עברי, because מכאן אמרו כל הקונה עבד עברי כקונה אדון לעצמו.
mikan amru kol hakoneh eved Ivri kekoneh adon le'atzmo. If you purchase
an עבד עברי, this isn't true by עבד כנעני, eved Kena'ani, but
it's like getting a master. Now the רמב"ן says what do you
mean a master? It's equivalent. I mean, okay, you have to provide
it for him, but he says no, because let's say you only
have one pillow. Okay, you only have one pillow, so you know,
you can't keep it for yourself because that would make you unequal,
it's not עמך. imach. You can't take the choice neither of us
will have it because that's a type of like a מידת סדום,
middat Sedom, like you know, you're just like, you know, you're just
holding back something that could be good for somebody for no reason.
So you have to give it to him, so actually if you
only had one, he would actually come before you. Okay. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, ויצא מעמך הוא ובניו עמו, veyatza imach hu uvanav imo,
he will leave you, he and children with him. So אמר רבי
שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, אם הוא נמכר בניו מי נמכרו, im hu
nimkar banav mi nimcharu, if he was sold, who sold his kids?
What do you mean his kids will leave with him? Okay, and
this is the kids leaving with him means his Jewish kids, right?
When the עבד עברי says I can't leave because I don't want
to abandon my wife and kids, they're slaves, and they're staying with
the master and those were non-Jewish. But here when it says he
goes free in the יובל Yovel with his kids, that means his
Jewish kids. So whoever bought his Jewish kids? Okay, מכאן שרבו חייב
במזונות בניו. mikan sherabo chayav bimezonos banav. I assume מזונות mezonos here
also means lodging. So from here you see that they were with
him, they he continued, as opposed to the reality of slaves, you
know, which where they rip apart families and all of that, here
the family was kept together and they were with him, and not
only that, the master had to provide for them. Okay, כיוצא בדבר
אתה
אומר, keyotza badavar atah omer, אם בעל אשה הוא ויצאה אשתו עמו,
im ba'al ishah hu veyatza ishto imo, you know,
if he was married his wife goes out. אמר רבי שמעון, amar
Rabbi Shimon, אם הוא נמכר אשתו מי נמכרה, im hu nimkar ishto
mi nimcherah, what do you mean go out with him? How was
she with him to begin with? מכאן שרבו חייב במזונות אשתו, mikan
sherabo chayav bimezonos ishto, has to also provide food for the wife.
וצריכה, u'tzricha, you need to say both. דאי אשמעינן בניו, de'ee ashme'inan
banav,
if it said provide for the kids, משום דלאו בני מעבד ועבדי,
mishum delav benei me'avad ve'avdi, because the kids can't work for themselves,
so obviously the master has to provide or more obvious than the
wife. אבל אשתו דבת מעבד ועבדי, aval ishto devas me'avad ve'avdi, but
the wife she can go ahead and work and feed herself, אימא
תעבוד ותאכל, eima ta'avod vesochal,
let her go ahead and master shouldn't have to pay for her,
let her go ahead and make get her own employment, okay, which
wasn't so easy in the ancient world. ואי אשמעינן אשתו, ve'ee ashme'inan
ishto, and if it said wife, דלאו דרכה להדורי, delav darchah lehadori,
a woman, you know, it's not the normal thing for her to
go around
begging, would not be seen as as proper, you know, putting herself
to be knocking on everybody's on strangers' doors. Okay, so she doesn't
have an opportunity to get funds through through begging. אבל בניו דדרכייהו
להדורי, aval banav dedarchyahu lehadori, but kids, you know... It would be
normal for them to go beg, אימא לא, Eima lo, maybe she
should say let them go beg. צריכה, Tzericha, so no, he has
to provide for both of them. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught, top of כ"ה ע"ב. Kaf Heh Amud Bet. We're only going
to go to the משנה Mishnah today. אם נאמר באזנו ובדלת, Im
ne'emar be'ozno ubadalet,
if it just said not באזנו ובדלת, be'ozno ubadalet, in his ear
and in the door, just said his ear in the door, הייתי
אומר, hayiti omer, ידקור כנגד אזנו בדלת, yidkor keneged ozno badalet, put
his ear against the door, but just pierce into the door. So
it has to
say באזנו be'ozno. ובדלת, it goes through his ear and through the
door. So דלת אין אזנו לא? dalet in ozno lo?
I would have thought
just the door
and not the ear? So it had to tell
me באזנו. Gemara says ואזנו לא, ve'ozno lo, how could I have
ever thought not the ear? והכתיב, vehashtiv, you're quoting a פסוק pasuk
in ויקרא, Vayikra, but you're דברים Devarim rather, you quote the פסוק
pasuk. in שמות, Shemot, ורצע אדניו את אזנו במרצע, veratza adonav et
ozno bammartze'a,
it says he should pierce his ear with an awl. So what
could I have thought? Obviously it was the ear. Okay fine. אלא
הייתי אומר, ella hayiti omer,
ירצענו לאזנו מבראי, yirtze'enu le'ozno mibbarai, first pierce the ear, you know,
on the outside, not when it's against the door, ויניחנו על הדלת
וידקור כנגד אזנו בדלת. veyannichennu al hadalet veyidkor keneged ozno badalet. You
do two things. ורצע אדניו את אזנו במרצע, veratza adonav et ozno
bammartze'a, you pierce the ear but not through the ear and through
the door in one piercing, you just pierce the ear. Then if
it had said ונתתה באזנו ובדלת, venatata be'ozno ubadalet, you know,
then you would have said, you know, you put his ear against
the door, you make a hole in the door and then you
somehow align them up or something. It would have been a little
crazy, but okay. Anyway, that's why it had to say באזנו ובדלת.
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar באזנו ובדלת, כיצד, keitzad, דוקר והולך עד שמגיע
אצל דלת. dokeir veholech ad shemmagi'a etzel dalet.
You pierce through the ear, the ear is against the door until
you get to the door. Okay, דלת, dalet, a door. שומע אני
בין עקורה ובין שאינה עקורה, shome'a ani bein akura uvein she'eina akura,
maybe whether it's detached or not detached. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar מזוזה,
mezuza, right? You said you put it in the lintel or the
door. מה מזוזה מעומד אף מזוזה, ma mezuza me'umad af mezuza, the
same way a מזוזה mezuza is something that's lentel, it's only called
a מזוזה mezuza when it is a doorframe, when it is actually
standing up, otherwise it's pieces of wood, אף דלת נמי מעומד. af
dalet nami me'umad. So the door also has to be standing up.
Okay.
Actually, I got that wrong. The lintel is the משקוף. mashkof. I
don't know what the מזוזה mezuza is called, the doorframe I guess.
Okay, רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai היה דורש את
המקרא הזה כמין חומר. hayah doresh et hammiqra zeh kemin chomer. רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai would explain this פסוק like
a חומר. chomer. What does חומר chomer mean? רש"י says it means
like a bag of spices, he gave a beautiful explanation. תוספות Tosafot
says it means story, and I actually like תוספות's Tosafot read. He
gave a story to explain as a משל mashal what's going on
in these פסוקים. pesukim. Let's take a look. מה נשתנה אזן מכל
האיברים שבגוף? ma nishtanna ozen mikkol ha'evarim shebbaguf? I'm sure everybody has
heard of this. Why was the ear the one that was chosen
to be pierced? אמר קדוש ברוך הוא, amar kadosh baruch hu, אזן
ששמעה קולי על הר סיני ozen sheshame'a koli al har sinai בשעה
שאמרתי כי לי בני ישראל עבדים besha'ah she'amarti ki li benei yisrael
avadim ולא עבדים לעבדים. velo avadim la'avadim. When I said on הר
סיני, Har Sinai, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael are my slaves and they're,
you know, they're only to be mine, I freed them so that
they would only be serving me, not serving other people. Okay.
והלך זה וקנה אדון לעצמו. vehalach zeh veqana adon le'atzmo. And this
one went and he bought a master for himself. He made himself
a slave to a slave in the sense of, you know, every
Jew is a slave or servant to God and now this person
made himself a slave to that servant to God. Anyway, so the
whole point was to be freed from slavery and now you're going
to go make yourself a slave? ירצע, yeratza, so that ear has
to be pierced. Okay, it's actually interesting, right? That משפטים Mishpatim starts
with the whole idea about slaves and freeing them after six years
and so on. It doesn't completely eradicate the institution of slavery, but
the idea that one of the first laws given after מעמד הר
סיני ma'amad har sinai is
about אנכי ה' אלהיך אשר הוצאתיך מארץ מצרים מבית עבדים, anochi adonay
elohecha asher hotzeticha me'eretz mitzrayim mibbeit avadim, right? And it's about how
do you sort of free your slave. Okay, רבי שמעון ברבי Rabbi
Shimon b'Rebbi היה דורש את המקרא הזה כמין חומר. hayah doresh et
hammiqra zeh kemin chomer. רבי שמעון ברבי Rabbi Shimon b'Rebbi also would
do a similar, gave a similar reading of this פסוק. מה נשתנה
דלת ומזוזה? ma nishtanna dalet umezuza? He focused on the door. Why
the door and the doorpost? מכל כלים שבבית. mikkol kelim shebbabbayit. אמר
קדוש ברוך הוא, amar kadosh baruch hu, דלת ומזוזה שהיו עדים במצרים
dalet umezuza shehayu edim bemitzrayim בשעה שפסחתי על המשקוף ועל שתי המזוזות.
besha'ah shepasachti al hammashkof ve'al shetei hamezuzot. They were the witnesses in
Egypt when I jumped over, you know, the lintel and the doorposts.
That's the word, doorpost. ואמרתי כי לי בני ישראל עבדים ולא עבדים
לעבדים ve'amarti ki li benei yisrael avadim velo avadim la'avadim and I
said they're my slaves, right? And they're meant to be free. והוצאתים
מעבדות לחרות, vehotzetim me'avdut lecherut, I took them out of slavery to
freedom. והלך זה וקנה אדון לעצמו vehalach zeh veqana adon le'atzmo and
he went ahead and he bought a master. ירצע בפניהם, yeratza bifnehem,
he should be pierced in the presence of the door. Like to
say, these are your עדים edim about how you should not be
making a slave, and you're still choosing to make yourself a slave.
Now, the first case, of course, you know, I don't understand, you
know, what about the first six years? I mean, the first six
years he was, he was a גנב, gannav, he shouldn't have been
a גנב, gannav, but he wasn't choosing slavery.
מוכר עצמו moker atzmo also, maybe the point is is that it's
one thing when, you know, your economic realities force you to do
it once, but to then go ahead and do it again, ועבדו
לעולם, ve'avado le'olam, that is something that really, you know, you have
to sort of symbolize how sort of wrong this is. Okay, we
will end here and we will pick up with the משנה Mishnah
tomorrow.